(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.2",
"generated_at": "2026-08-22T02:30:03.343518",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
手にしたもの以外が綺麗に見えた
Everything other than what I held looked so beautiful.
「どうせこんなものか」が口癖だった
"This is as good as it gets" was my catchphrase.
うすら笑いばかりが得意になった
I got good at just giving a faint smile.
でも一番笑えるのはこのプライドだ
But the funniest part of all is this pride of mine.
一生懸命なんかすべて無駄だったんだよ
Giving it my all was just a complete waste of time.
ああもう嫌になった
Ah, I'm so sick of it.
「逃げたくない」って聞こえて、これは僕の声？
"I don't want to run away," I heard—was that my voice?
1回10回100回1000回挑戦を続けるよ
Once, ten, a hundred, a thousand times, I'll keep trying.
まだ足りないって思っている
I still feel like it's not enough.
やまない雨の中
Inside the endless rain,
ずっと考えて考えて考えて
I keep thinking, thinking, and thinking,
見つけ出せ僕だけの滑走路を
to find my very own runway.
証明したいんだよね、そうだろう？そうだろう？
I want to prove it, don't I? Right? Right?
焦り上がる心拍数に嘘をつくように
As if to lie to my racing heartbeat,
自分を落ち着付ける皮肉はいらない
I don't need any irony to calm myself down.
それを高揚感に置き換えたらさ
If I replace that with a sense of euphoria,
今日もまた挑むべきハードルがほら見えただろう？
can't you see another hurdle to challenge today?
葛藤の隙間で
In the gaps of our struggles,
錆びない声名をひねり出せるか
can I squeeze out an unfading reputation?
みんな！3周年のフェスに来てくれて ありがとう！
Everyone! Thank you so much for coming to the 3rd-anniversary festival!
楽しんでいきましょう！
Let's enjoy ourselves!
なんでもないような顔して犬 ご機嫌損ねて「バウワウ」と
Looking indifferent like a dog, in a bad mood, saying "bow wow,"
今日は レイニーデイ レイニーデイ
Today is a rainy day, a rainy day.
闇の上で少女が泣き濡れては りんご飴を舐めて空を見た
A girl crying in the dark, licking a candy apple and looking at the sky.
今日は レイニーデイ レイニーデイ
Today is a rainy day, a rainy day.
カンテラ持って 歌って
Singing with a lantern in hand,
明日の準備は 駆し慣れて
getting used to preparing for tomorrow,
賛美の言葉を歌おうぜ ほらハイネリーダンラ
let's sing words of praise, hey, heigh-ho, rain or shine!
魚の面で歌って 有刺鉄線は飛び越えて
Singing with a fish mask, jumping over barbed wire,
遊ぼうぜ、笑おうぜ！
let's play, let's laugh!
くだらない愛を歌う この街の中
Singing meaningless love in this town,
明かりを灯せば 何にもない
if you light a lamp, there's nothing else at all.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, ほら合図で君に会いに行こう
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, look, let's go meet you on cue.
新しい日を迎えに行こう
Let's go welcome a new day!
なんだばだらららだった
Na-na-ba-da-ra-ra-ra-tat-ta,
なんだばだらららだったタ
na-na-ba-da-ra-ra-ra-tat-ta.
何て名前かも忘れて また 赤電話が鳴り「フワウワ」と
Forgetting even what my name is, the payphone rings "fuwa uwa" again.
今日も レイニーデイ レイニーデイ
Today is also a rainy day, a rainy day.
煙草の煙に濡れちゃって また 無世界(むせかえる)路地裏去って歩いてた
Getting wet in cigarette smoke, walking away through a choking alleyway.
レイニーデイ レイニーデイ
Rainy day, rainy day.
アンテナ立ったらもういいかい 商店街から顔出して
Is it time yet? Peeking out from the shopping district,
泣いてる子には歌おうぜ ほらハイネリーダンラ
let's sing to the crying child, hey, heigh-ho, rain or shine!
さよならばっかり詰め込んで 二律背反を背負い込んで
Stuffing ourselves with goodbyes, carrying paradoxes on our backs,
泣かないで 揺れないで
don't cry, don't waver.
右手の上で回る地球儀を
The globe spinning on your right hand,
左手の火で照らそうか
shall we illuminate it with the fire in your left hand?
空の色が変わる その時に 胸に残るのは君のこと
When the color of the sky changes, what remains in my heart is you.
雨宿り駄菓子屋で 神様の帰りを待った
Waiting for god's return at the candy store while taking shelter from the rain.
さあ 歌おうか 羊の歌！
Now, let's sing the sheep's song!
ああ 迷い駄菓子屋で 神様の帰りを持った
Ah, getting lost in the candy store, waiting for god's return...
さあ 歌おうか 羊の歌
Now, let's sing the sheep's song!
君の手の そのカンテラが
That lantern in your hands
全てを照らす 太陽なんだ
is the sun that illuminates everything!
君が歌を歌う この街の中
Singing in this town where you sing songs,
明かりを灯せば 素敵なこと
lighting a lamp makes it wonderful.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, ほら合図で君に会いに行こう
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, look, let's go meet you on cue.
新しい日を迎えに行こう
Let's go welcome a new day!
トンネルの先には何がある?
What lies beyond the tunnel?
街の外に踏み出して行く
Stepping out beyond the town.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, ほら合図で君に会いに行こう
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, look, let's go meet you on cue.
新しい日を迎えに行こう
Let's go welcome a new day!
なんでもないような顔して犬
Looking as if nothing's wrong, a dog
ご機嫌損ねてる「バウバウ」と
is in a bad mood, going "bow-wow"...
今日は レイニーデイ
Today is a rainy day.
屋根の上で少女が泣き濡れては
On the roof, a girl weeps and gets soaked,
林檎飴を舐めて空を見た
licking a candy apple as she looks at the sky.
今日は レイニーデイ
Today is a rainy day.
カンテラ持って歌うたって
Holding a lantern, singing a song,
明日の準備を携えて
with preparations for tomorrow in hand,
賛美の言葉歌おうぜ
let's sing words of praise!
ほらハイネリラリンラ
Look, heigh-ho-rilla-rilla!
魚の面で歌うたって
Wearing a fish mask, singing a song,
有刺鉄線を飛び越えて
leaping over barbed wire,
遊ぼうぜ、笑おうぜ！
let's play, let's laugh!
くどらない愛を歌う この街の中
Singing uncomplicated love in this town,
明かりを灯せば何にもない
if you light a lamp, there is nothing there.
1,2,3,4,5, ほら合図で君に会いに行こうぜ
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, come on, let's go meet you with a signal!
無数に広がる夢と願いが
Countless spreading dreams and wishes
夜に飲み込まれ 姿を消していく
are swallowed by the night, fading away.
試されている この答えと 僕の覚悟はホンモノか？
Are this tested answer and my resolve the real deal?
まだ終わりじゃないな
It's not over yet.
喜びを吸い込んで 不安を吐き出して
Inhaling joy, exhaling anxiety,
生かされている意味を ずっと探してるんだ
I've been searching all along for the meaning of life.
たとえ ヒトリゴトになったとしても
Even if it becomes just talking to myself,
これが 僕の 確かな 光と 祈り
this is my certain light and prayer.
誠実に生きることで
By living with sincerity,
強く なれると知った
I learned I could become strong.
見逃すな day by day
Don't miss it, day by day.
ただ迷い彷徨っていくつのも日々を追い越したんだ
I've outrun so many days of just wandering and hesitating.
wow, oh-oh-oh
生き残ったこの世界で
In this world where I survived,
新しい眩しい幕開けを迎えに行こうか
shall we go welcome a new, dazzling curtain-raiser?
愛すべきはずの大切なものが
The precious things we ought to love
僕らしさをまた一つ腐らせていく
are rotting our uniqueness one by one.
守ると決めたこの正義が
This justice I decided to protect
時に誰かを傷つけてしまう どこで間違えた？
sometimes ends up hurting someone. Where did I go wrong?
涙を飲み干して 幸せ噛み締めて
Swallowing tears, savoring happiness,
この存在の意味を ほら味わいながら
tasting the meaning of this existence,
例えば 全てがゼロになっても ありのままの 僕に戻るだけ
even if everything becomes zero, I'll just return to my true self.
重ねた step by step
Piling up step by step,
すれ違い間違い傷ついてもまだここに立ってんだ
passing by, making mistakes, getting hurt, yet I'm still standing right here.
wow, oh-oh-oh
悩み抜いた長い夜が 悔やみない逃げないたった一つの僕のやり方
The long night I worried through—my one and only way of doing things without regret or escape.
朱色の空に黒が溶けて絡む夜明け
Dawn where black melts and tangles into a vermilion sky,
現実と夢混ざり合う狭間
the space where reality and dreams mix
滲む月夜西の空に堕ちて行く頃
When the bleeding moonlit night falls into the western sky,
玄冬の暮れ目新春の息吹雪月風花
winter dusk, the breath of early spring, snow, moon, flowers, and wind.
見逃すな day by day
Don't miss it, day by day.
ただ迷い彷徨っていくつのも日々を追い越したんだ
I've outrun so many days of just wandering and hesitating.
wow, oh-oh-oh
生き残ったこの世界で 新しい眩しい幕開けを迎えに行こうか
In this world where I survived, shall we go welcome a new, dazzling curtain-raiser?
巡り巡る brand new day
Spinning and spinning brand new day,
泣いても逃げても幸せをいつも願っていたんだ
crying or running away, I always wished for happiness.
wow, oh-oh-oh
いつか終わるその日まで 新しい眩しい幕開けを迎えに行こうか
Until the day it eventually ends, shall we go welcome a new, dazzling curtain-raiser?
白の空に黒が溶けて絡む夜明け
Dawn where black melts and tangles into a white sky,
現実は夢と混ざり合う狭間
the space where reality and dreams mix
滲む月よ西の空に堕ちて行く頃
When the bleeding moon falls into the western sky,
言問の暮れ新春の息吹雪月風花
dusk of words, the breath of early spring, snow, moon, flowers, and wind.
見逃すな day by day
Don't miss it, day by day.
ただ迷い彷徨っていくつのも日々を追い越したんだ
I've outrun so many days of just wandering and hesitating.
wow, oh-oh-oh
生き残ったこの世界で 新しい眩しい幕開けを迎えに行こうか
In this world where I survived, shall we go welcome a new, dazzling curtain-raiser?
巡り巡る brand new day
Spinning and spinning brand new day,
泣いても逃げても幸せをいつも願っていたんだ
crying or running away, I always wished for happiness.
wow, oh-oh-oh
いつか終わるその日まで 新しい眩しい幕開けを迎えに行こうか
Until the day it eventually ends, shall we go welcome a new, dazzling curtain-raiser?
迎えに行こうか 迎えに行こうか
Shall we go welcome it, shall we go welcome it?
こんばんは！
Good evening!
どーもどーも！
Hello, hello!
うわ、すごいねー！
Whoa, this is amazing!
広いねー！
It's so spacious!
角巻わため3周年ということで、
Celebrating Tsunomaki Watame's
今日はずっとやりたかった野外ロックフェスをやらせていただきます！
3rd anniversary, we're holding the outdoor rock festival I've always wanted to do!
今日のハッシュタグわかる人ー？
Who knows today's hashtag?
わかんないのかなー？わかる人いないのかなー？
Don't you know? Is there no one who knows?
わためはわかるわかるわかる！はいわためちゃん！はーい！
Watame knows! Yes, Watame-chan! Hii!
えー今日はですね、こちら！ハッシュタグ「わためフェス」わためフェス！
Um, today, here! The hashtag is 'WataFes', WataFes!
リピートアフターミー、わためフェス！
Repeat after me, WataFes!
とってもわかりやすいですね！このわためフェスをつけて、スクショとかもねいっぱい撮って、いっぱいバズバズあげていただければあとでねわためが見ますんでよろしくお願いいたします！
It's very easy to understand! If you use this WataFes, take lots of screenshots, and post them like crazy, Watame will check them out later, so please do!
あとライブ来てくださーい！
And please come to the live!
そして、こちら！今日は見せたいものがある！
And, here! Today I have something to show you!
ほーい！
Here!
こんばんはー！わためのみんなー！
Good evening! Everyone to Wata-me!
今日はわためロックフェス2022がありますんでお集まりください！いますぐにー！
Today is Wata Rock Fes 2022, so please gather! Right now!
ということでね、この拡声器を今日この時のために作っていただきました！
So, they made this megaphone for me just for this occasion today!
えーでもね、このあとアフターライブまで使う機材がございますのでよろしくお願いいたします！アフターライブ来てくださーい！
Um, but, since we have equipment to use until the after-party live, please take care of it! Please come to the after-party live!
では置きます。
Now I'll put it down.
このあとゲストパートもありますんでみんな盛り上がっていけるかー！
There's also a guest part coming up, can everyone get hyped?!
もーたーもーたー！ゲスト来るんだぞー！もーたーもーたー！コメント書けー！
Mo-ta-mo-ta! Guests are coming! Mo-ta-mo-ta! Write comments!
いいねあったまったね！ほんならぶち上がっていくぜー！
Alright, we're warmed up! Now let's rock out!
絆を 自ら 引き裂いた
I tore the bond myself
as judgment
吊り上げて …
lifting up...
mind as Judgment
名も無き寓話 嗜む人の
An unnamed parable, tasting human
闇よ語れ shade and fear
Darkness, speak of shade and fear
蘇る魔の群れ
A swarm of resurrected demons
淀む境目 手招いて
Beckoning at the stagnant boundary
時の果てさ dead end town
The end of time, dead end town
死神の笑い声
The Grim Reaper's laughter
償っても 償っても
Even if you redeem, even if you compensate
贖い死す 定義には
In the definition of dying in atonement
did you see ? did you say ?
did you see? did you say?
非で穿つ
Piercing with non-existence
守るべき命抱いて 重さが愛だと信じてた
Holding the life to protect, believing that weight was love
堕落への駆け引きでも 裏切りならば
Even in the bargaining for corruption, if it's betrayal
trust of a heart
大切な世界 見つめながら
While staring at the precious world
mind as judgment
give up ! you know ! give up !
give up! you know! give up!
祈りを灰に弄れ
Playing with prayer into ashes
荒れた鼓動の ark with life
Ark with life of a rough heartbeat
溺れる者達へ 求める光を与えよう
To those who drown, let's give the sought-after light
朽ちる地底の zero count down
Zero count down in the decaying underground
断末の叫び声
Scream of agony
怯えている 嘆いている
Frightened, lamenting
欲の香り撒いたのでしょう？
Did you scatter the scent of greed?
do that fake ! do that fake !
do that fake! do that fake!
お選びなさい
Choose
滅びの日が来る定めに
To the destiny that the day of destruction will come
言葉に意味さえ無いのだなら
If words don't even have meaning
貴方から唱えて
Chant from you
今切実な願い
Now, an earnest wish
keep your faith
侮るべきは諦めの生
What should be despised is the life of resignation
nine days wonder , all above
nine days wonder, all above
残り少ない さあ逃げたらどうよ？
There's little left, come on, what if you run?
恐れ満ちて hold my breath , if you run
Filled with fear, hold my breath, if you run
滅びの日が来る定めに
To the destiny that the day of destruction will come
言葉に意味さえ無いのだなら
If words don't even have meaning
貴方から唱えて
Chant from you
今切実な願い
Now, an earnest wish
無垢な命抱いて
Holding an innocent life
重さが愛なのか 私の姿 まだ裏切る前の
Is the weight love? Before my figure betrays yet
trust of a heart
大切な世界 見つめながら
While staring at the precious world
mind as judgment
get out ! i shot ! get out !
get out! i shot! get out!
一人暗い部屋ん中で
In a dark room all alone,
踊り出そう夜が終るまで
Let's dance until the night ends.
脳内では主人公でいさせて
Let me be the protagonist in my mind,
さあ始めよう
Now then, let's begin.
もしもの話なんです
It's a "what if" story,
例えば君の前に
For example, if right before you...
7, 6, 5, 4, 3, 2, 1, Secret Weapon!
コンビニで見つけた態度だけデカイ客は
That rude customer I found at the convenience store
注意しても聞かないし
wouldn't listen even when warned,
殴ってやったんだ
so I punched him.
シラザシラザ 又自分を憎んで
Unknowingly, hating myself once more,
シラザシラザ 又自分を隠して
Unknowingly, hiding myself once more,
シラザシラザ 又自分を愛して
Unknowingly, loving myself once more,
四畳半 深夜二時 電気はつかない
A four-and-a-half tatami room at 2 AM, the lights won't turn on.
満たされない夜よ明けないで
Oh unsatisfied night, do not dawn,
今日だけはこのままでいさせて
Let me remain just like this for today.
他の誰かのフリして生きていくだけなら
If I'm just going to live pretending to be someone else,
こんなに楽なのに
How easy it would be.
やったー！
Yay!
うれしい！わため3周年おめでとう！
Yay! Happy 3rd anniversary, Watame!
ありがとう！うれしいじゃん！
Thank you! I'm so happy!
りずちゃんもそらちゃんも来てくれてありがとうございます！
Thank you so much LIZ and Sora for coming!
こちらこそ！
Our pleasure!
抱きしめちゃうぞー
I'm gonna give you a big hug!
ラムサンドです！
It's a lamb sandwich!
これラムサンド？ サンドイッチですー
Is this a lamb sandwich? A sandwich!
スクショタイム！
Screenshot time!
イエーイ！
Yeah!
暑い！やばい！うれしい！
It's hot! So intense! But I'm so happy!
すごく素敵な野外ステージだよね！
What a wonderful outdoor stage!
わためとがギターとベースをドラムを担当している
Watame and co. are playing guitar, bass, and drums.
あ、わためいた！かわいい！
Ah, there's Watame! So cute!
そしてあっちじゃんベースが
And over there, the bass...
針金眼鏡かけてる！
She's wearing wire-rimmed glasses!
髪もきっちり決めてるね！
Her hair is styled so neatly too!
おっ、ドラムのわためいた！
Oh, there's Watame on drums!
会場にはいっぱいいますね、わためとが！
There are so many Watames all over the venue!
本当に素敵なステージに来れて嬉しい！
We're so happy to be on such a wonderful stage!
この曲も歌いたかったんで絶対あると思ってさ！嬉しい！知ってた？この曲！
We wanted to sing this song too, so we knew it had to be here! So happy! Did you know this song?
初めてだった！初めて歌ったそう！
It was our first time! We sang it for the first time!
わためが教えてくれて！めちゃくちゃいい曲でしたね！
Watame taught it to us! Such an amazing song!
覚えてくれたの？コーラスとかもね、ハモりも結構いっぱいあって！事前に頑張って！
You learned it? There were so many chorus parts and harmonies! We worked really hard beforehand!
ありがとうございます！手伝っていただいて！ありがとうございます！素敵なステージになりました！
Thank you so much! For helping us out! Thank you! It turned out to be such a wonderful stage!
素晴らしいね3周年だ！
It's wonderful, 3rd anniversary!
え、また歌ってくれる？ぜひぜひぜひ！
Will you sing with us again? By all means, absolutely!
赤、黄色、青で信号機！信号機コンビで！
Red, yellow, and blue—a traffic light trio!
やろうよまた一緒に！よろしくおねがいします！
Let's do it together again! We look forward to it!
ありがとうね！この後もずっとね、みんな頑張る！
Thank you so much! We'll keep doing our best from here on too!
A reaper’s playin’ for keeps, so peep the scythe that i swing
Make a believer outta doubters, how ’outchall call me the king?
Make a believer outta doubters, how 'outchall call me the king?
If it’s a battle you’re after, then leave the rapping to me
Garou garou the wolf is hungry for her senpai, the sheep!!
麻利夫のイモアシ　酸性リサイコマジン
With a brilliant phrasing, even better than imagined, honestly!
でも本物のラッパーならばまずはディスはキング
But if you're a real rapper, disses are forbidden first!
アンチディススタイルつまり応援ラップ
Anti-diss style, meaning an cheering rap!
ハローハローわためが...
Hello hello, Watame is...
a reaper's play in ' for keeps , so peep the scythe that i swing
A reaper's playin' for keeps, so peep the scythe that I swing
make a believer outta doubters , how ' bout you call me the king ?
Make a believer outta doubters, how 'bout you call me the king?
if it ' s a battle you ' re after , then leave the rapping to me
If it's a battle you're after, then leave the rapping to me
garou garou the wolf is hungry for her senpai , the sheep ! !
Garou garou the wolf is hungry for her senpai, the sheep!!
maa rippa na ii mawashi souzou yori saikou maji
Such fine phrasing, even better than I imagined, seriously!
demo honmono no rappaa naraba mazu wa disu wa kinku
But if you're a real rapper, disses are forbidden first!
anchi disu sutairu tsumari ouen rappu
Anti-diss style, meaning an encouraging rap.
haroo haroo wa tame garu uru senpai da shi
Hello, hello, Watame is a noisy senpai, after all!
ain’t used to “ raising up ” for raps but guess i’ll give it a shot
I ain't used to "raising up" for raps, but guess I'll give it a shot
excuses go in the trash so give it all that you got !
Excuses go in the trash, so give it all that you got!
i’ll script a cheer or a curse , for when calli is next up to bat
I'll script a cheer or a curse for when Calli is next up to bat
gonna kick that shit in reverse , i’m wishing you’ll crush your boy flat
Gonna kick that shit in reverse, I'm wishing you'll crush your boy flat
senaka osu dake nara hora ne kantan desho
It's so simple if you just push me on the back, right?
onaka kara koe dashite mazu wa ouen shiyou
Let's let out our voices from the belly and cheer first!
kan kyaku ga kimeru kore ga good or bad
The audience decides if it's good or bad!
iku ze 3 ・ 2 ・ 1
Here we go, 3, 2, 1!
nayan de nayan de mou night and day tte betsu ni warukunai yo nee
Worrying and worrying, night and day, it's not actually bad, right?
how ’ s it hanging , watamelon ? aren ’ t you feeling the heat ?
How's it hanging, Watamelon? Aren't you feeling the heat?
cuz when it comes to rappin ’ compliments , i ’ m the reaper to beat !
'Cuz when it comes to rappin' compliments, I'm the reaper to beat!
gotta let you know your flow is look in ’ so pro and the bars that you ’ re spittin ’ are fire
Gotta let you know your flow is lookin' so pro and the bars that you're spittin' are fire
isn ’ t it funny ? they want me to ” kill ’ em with kindness , ” i ’ ll never get tired !
Isn't it funny? They want me to "kill 'em with kindness," I'll never get tired!
hat ka butte gokigen na wa tame no head
Wearing a hat, Watame's happy head—
wa to kizu keba hini ku ? yokunai ne
Realizing it's irony? That's not good, huh?
orosempai da shi
Watame senpai!
tsumari aite sura mo kimochi yoku saseru furou ga mazu wa hoshii no
In other words, I first want a flow that makes even my opponent feel good.
ima no wa genten ! waza to or tennen ?
Was that the starting point! On purpose or natural?
is that a trick or a fact ?
Is that a trick or a fact?
checkmate , i ’ m down on my knees
Checkmate, I'm down on my knees
goddamn , i take it all back
Goddamn, I take it all back
this sheep has got so much ” steez ”
This sheep has got so much "steez"
hold up , that shit ’ s kinda cringe …
Hold up, that shit's kinda cringe...
it ’ s just i ’ m aiming to please
It's just I'm aiming to please
you ’ re lines are the baddest , hey listen , it ’ s praise if in english
Your lines are the baddest, hey listen, it's praise if in english
i ’ m makin ’ your victory of breeze ! ! you copy ?
I'm makin' your victory a breeze!! You copy?
arigatou me too watashi mo
Thank you, me too, I think so as well
ari kamo tte omou wa tame no rappu ga
Watame's rap might actually be good,
dakara maa doui mo toreta koto da shi watame no kachi tte koto de ii ka na ?
So since we've agreed, is it okay if Watame wins?
right , no more play in ’ , it ’ s time to get slay in ’
Right, no more playin', it's time to get slayin'
i ’ ll praise and i ’ ll raise you ’ till dead beats start pray in ’
I'll praise and I'll raise you 'till dead beats start prayin'
the lines i be lay in ’ betraying me , flaying me open , alive , maybe dead , painful though it be
The lines I be layin' betraying me, flaying me open, alive, maybe dead, painful though it be
nobody best try to mess ’ with the sheep when she makes a cut , you can bet she cut deep
Nobody best try to mess with the sheep, when she makes a cut, you can bet she cut deep
more than mutton , she ’ s push in ’ your buttons , so honestly watame oughta be takin ’ the lead !
More than mutton, she's pushin' your buttons, so honestly, Watame oughta be takin' the lead!
honki no wa tame rappu ka masu ze mazu wa nani ga ii ?
I'm dropping serious Watame rap, what do you want first?
dondon at sumate iku shisen no saki wa waki pai
The gazes gathering more and more are fixed on armpits and boobs!
hentai zenkai tensai senpai genkai benkai
Full-throttle pervert, genius senpai, limit, excuse—
iku ze 3 ・ 2 ・ 1
Let's go, 3, 2, 1!
nayan de nayan de mou night and day tte betsu ni warukunai yo nee
Worrying and worrying, night and day, it's not actually bad, right?
maa yan demo yan demo ganbare tte iwaretaku wa nai yo nee
Well, even when I'm depressed, I don't want to be told "Hang in there!"
the reaper and the sheep are the best for you all
ashita mo asatte mo soba ni iyou
Let's stay by each other's side tomorrow and the day after too.
waratte waratte ? mo unan ya nen
Laugh, laugh? What is this nonsense?
warawareru made nait are
Cry until people laugh at you!
peace !
Peace!
iku ze 3 ・ 2 ・ 1
Here we go, 3, 2, 1!
nayan de nayan de mou night and day tte betsu ni warukunai yo nee
Worrying and worrying, night and day, it's not actually bad, right?
maa yan demo yan demo ganbare tte iwaretaku wa nai yo nee
Well, even when I'm depressed, I don't want to be told "Hang in there!"
the reaper and the sheep are the best for you all
ashita mo asatte mo soba ni iyou
Let's stay by each other's side tomorrow and the day after too.
waratte waratte ? mou nan ya nen
Laugh, laugh? What is this nonsense?
warawareru made nait are
Cry until people laugh at you!
peace !
Peace!
one more time one more time
watame senpai mou aridasu yo
Watame-senpai, that's not enough!
motto ikeru yo nee
We can go another round, right?
shini kami dakedo... te o ne
My soul is crying, but my body—
はーい！やったー！
Hii! Yay!
皆さん応援ありがとうみんな！楽しかった！
Thank you all for cheering, everyone! That was so fun!
カリちゃん来てくれてありがとー！
Thanks for coming, Calli-chan!
はーい、毎回楽しいね、ワタメ先輩！
Yay, it's always fun, Watame-senpai!
ねー！本当に誘ってくれてありがとうございます！
Right! Thank you so much for inviting me!
こちらこそカリちゃんのね、ソロライブのときも呼んでくれてありがとうございます！
No, thank you for inviting me to your solo live too, Calli-chan!
もちろんです、いつでもね、呼んでくださいね。
Of course, please invite me anytime.
そして、素敵な3年、おめでとうございまーす！
And congratulations on a wonderful 3 years!
ありがとうー！うれしー！
Thank you! I'm so happy!
わー、めちゃめちゃ素晴らしい先輩、本当に憧れな人です、ワタメ先輩。大好き！
Wow, Watame-senpai is truly an amazing, inspiring person. I love you!
えー照れる！ワタメも大好き！
Eh, I'm getting shy! I love you too!
嬉しいー！あー、もうドキドキしてる。I love you!
I'm so happy! Ah, my heart is pounding. I love you!
I love you too, senpai! いつも頑張ってるね、先輩。
I love you too, senpai! You're always working so hard, senpai.
そんなことないよ、カリちゃんだって！
Not at all, you too, Calli-chan!
いや、本当に、なんか、すごいリスペクトしてるよ、先輩。
No, really, like, I respect you so much, senpai.
The very busy reaper and the very busy sheep!
これからもね、ラップでも歌でも頑張りましょう！頑張りましょう！
Let's keep doing our best in rap and singing too! Let's do our best!
そうだね、チンプリラッパー。そう、でも次回ね、負けないよ。
That's right. Chim-puri rapper. Yeah, but next time, I won't lose!
いや、次も勝つね！勝ちます！勝つね、次も！
No, I'll win next time too! I'll win! I'll win next time too!
えー絶対勝つ！やだ、で、でもじゃあ次も歌ってくれるってこと？
Eh, I'll definitely win! No, wait, then does that mean you'll sing with me next time too?
ラウンド2？ラウンド2？ちょっと、なんか、スタミナトレーニングしなきゃいけない。
Round 2? Round 2? I need to do some stamina training.
The very busy reaper da ne, so yeah, 運動したいよ。頑張ります、先輩。
The very busy reaper then, so yeah, I want to exercise. I'll do my best, senpai.
わかった！また次一緒に歌うと、もちろん です！
Understood! And singing together next time, of course!
呼んでくださいね、いつでもね。ありがとうだよ、嬉しい！
Please invite me anytime. Thank you so much, I'm so happy!
はい、じゃあ頑張ってね！頑張る！ありがとう！ありがとう！
Yes, then do your best! I'll do my best! Thank you! Thank you!
本当にみんな、See you!
Truly everyone, see you!
君たちって何でもかんでも分類区別たがる
You guys want to categorize and classify everything.
人はなぜか分類したがる 修正があるとかないとか
Humans for some reason want to classify things, whether there's a fix or not.
この世の中に2種類の人間がいるとか言う
Saying there are two types of people in this world—
君たちが標的
you guys are the target.
持ってて持てないやつとか
Those who have it and those who don't,
ちゃんとやるやつとやってないやつとか
those who do it properly and those who don't,
陰キャ陽キャとか
introverts or extroverts?
君らは分類しないとどうにも落ち着かない
You guys can't settle down unless you categorize things.
気づかない本能の側道を覗いていかない？
Peeking outside the unconscious instincts, aren't you?
気分が乗らない？ つまりそれはそんなシンプルじゃない
Not in the mood? In other words, it's not that simple.
もっと曖昧で繊細で不鮮明な何か
More ambiguous, delicate, and unclear.
例えば持ってんのに出せないやつ やってないのにいけないやつ…
For example, those who have it but can't show it, or those who get anxious pretending to know...
所詮アンタはギフトed
After all, you're gifted...
アタシは普通の主婦ですと
and I'm just an ordinary housewife.
それは良いんでしょう？ 素晴らしいんでしょう？
That's fine, isn't it? Wonderful, isn't it?
不可能な証明の完成なんじゃない？
Isn't that the completion of proving the impossible?
夢を持てなんて言ってない
I'm not saying you should have dreams,
そんな無責任にはしないから
and I won't be that irresponsible.
ただその習性に噛食われないで
Just don't let that habit consume you.
そんなhabit捨てる度見えてくる 君の価値
Every time you let go of that habit, your true value becomes clear.
俺たちだって動物 こーゆーのって好物
We're animals too, this kind of thing is our favorite.
ここまでにされたらどう？ 普通腹の底からこふつこふつと
What do you think now that I've said all this?
俺たちだって動物 故に持ち得るoriginalな習性
We're animals too, therefore we have our own original habits.
自分で自分を分類するなよ 壊して見せるよその場habit
Don't classify yourself, break that bad habit.
大人の俺が言っちゃいけない事言っちゃうけど 説教するってぶっちゃけ快楽
Adults shouldn't say this, but preaching is actually a pleasure.
酒の肴にすりゃもう傑作 でも君も進むきっかけになりゃ
It's a masterpiece when you use it as a topic of conversation over drinks.
そりゃそれでwin-winじゃん？ こりゃこれで残念じゃん？
Then it's a win-win, right? This is a pity.
そもそもそれって君次第だし その後なんか俺興味ないわけ
It's up to you anyway, and I don't care what happens after that.
この先君はどうしたい？ って人に問われる事自体
What do you want to do from here on out? Being asked that question itself...
終わりじゃないと信じたい けどそうじゃなきゃかなり非常事態
I want to believe it's not the end, but if it's not, it's a major crisis.
君たちがその分類された普通の箱でくすぶってるからさ
Because you're stuck in those categorized ordinary boxes.
俺は人生イージーモード ずっとそこで眠っててやらさ
I'm living an easy life, just sleeping there in my thirties.
俺はそもそもスペックが低いだから足掻いて藻掻いてみにくく吠えた
I'm just not that capable, so I struggled and screamed ugly.
俺のあの頃を分類したら 誰の目から見ても明らか
If you categorize my past, it's obvious to anyone.
すぐ世の中金だとか愛だとか運だとか縁だとか なぜ2文字で片付けちゃうの
Why do you reduce everything to money, love, luck, or fate?
俺たちはもっと曖昧で 複雑で不鮮明な何か
We're more ambiguous, complex, and unclear.
悟ったふりして誇るなよ
Don't pretend to be enlightened and arrogant.
君に自分を分類する能力なんかない
You don't have the ability to categorize yourself.
壊して見せるよその場habit
Break that bad habit.
俺たちだって動物 こーゆーのって好物
We're animals too, this is our favorite thing.
ここまでにされたらどう？ 普通腹の底からこふつこふつと
What do you say to that? Normally, it would boil up from the depths of your stomach.
俺たちだって動物 故に持ち得るoriginalな習性
We're animals too, we have our own original instincts.
自分で自分を分類するなよ 壊して見せるよその場habit
Don't classify yourself, break that bad habit.
俺たちだって動物 こーゆーのって好物
We're animals too, this is our favorite thing.
ここまでにされたらどう？ 普通腹の底からこふつこふつと
What do you say to that? Normally, it would boil up from the depths of your stomach.
俺たちだって動物 故に持ち得るoriginalな習性
We're animals too, we have our own original instincts.
自分で自分を分類するなよ 壊して見せるよその場habit
Don't classify yourself, break that bad habit.
次のゲストは？ るいちゃん！らみぃちゃん！
Our next guests are... Lui-chan, Lamy-chan!
こんにちは！
Hello!
おめでとうございます！ありがとうございます！
Congratulations on your 3rd anniversary! Thank you very much!
ということでこの3人で今日はコントを
So today the three of us will be doing a skit.
はい、やらせて頂きたいなと！
Yes, we'd like to do that!
じゃあ決め台詞言ってもいいですか？
Can I say my catchphrase?
はい、お願いします！決め台詞は、
Yes, please! My catchphrase is...
シナジーなし！
No synergy!
なんで？！
Why?!
違うだろ！
That's not it!
あります？
Is there one?
だって
Well...
女騎士、女忍者、女羊ぐらい？
About one female samurai, female ninja, female knight?
そうだな。
Yeah, right.
女って付けりゃ。
You just add "female."
女のジビはちょっと。
The "female" vibe is a bit...
女のジビでしょ？
Right? "Female vibe"?
だめ？
No good?
ね、確かに。
Right.
じゃあ、ただの騎士？
Then just a knight...
食べ物に、
If it turns into food,
食べ物になったら
if it becomes food...
いいんじゃない？
Isn't that good?
食べ物になったら？
If it becomes food?
ラム牛丼とか。
Rum-gyudon or something.
牛丼、あ、じゃ集団生まれだよ。
Gyudon? I was born as Shudan!
あ、生まれた！生まれたよ。
Oh, born! Born!
牛丼なのか羊なのか。
Is it gyudon or is it a sheep?
じゃあ、私がそれをね、調理すれば、あ、羊が、あ、綺麗に切ったら
If I cook that, um, sheep energy...
生まれた！生まれた！
Born! Born!
お、ずん！
Oh, zoom!
生まれたよ。
Born!
だてわ... うまれ...
Datte wa... Born...
レスポンド、生まれた！
Respond, born!
コラボ、おの待ちそれをお願い。
Collaboration? I'm asking for that.
お願いします。ラムドン、ラムドン。
Please. Ramudon, Ramudon.
いやいや、違う、違う、違う。
No, no, different, different, different.
違う、違う。
Different, different.
このステージで、ええ、
At this stage, um...
やるといえば、
to do it, I mean...
え、今度じゃないの？
Wait, isn't this it?
違う、違う。
Different, different.
Wait, different.
今度じゃないよ。
Not this.
ら・く・に・く？
Ra-ku-ni-ku?
違う！違う！
Different! Different!
ライブ！あ、ライブ！
Live! Ah, live!
ライブ、ライブ！
Live, live!
じゃあ次の曲をね、聴いてもらったら、
So, the next song, please listen to it.
うん。
Um...
すげえアウトと思ってくれると思うんだよね。
I think you'll think it's a huge hit, you know.
これでラムドンシナジーが生まれるんですね。
With that, Ramudon synergy is born, right?
そう、反応がわかる。
So, reactions will come.
と思うので。
Because I think so.
行くぞ！
Let's go!
大丈夫かな？
Are you okay?
行くぞ！
Let's go!
行くぜ！
それでは聞いてください。
Then please listen.
のびしろ
Nobishiro.
サボり方とか甘え方とか
Laziness or spoiling,
逃げ方とか言い訳の仕方とか
running away or making excuses,
やっと覚えてきた身につけてきた
I've finally learned and picked them up.
柔らかい頭
Soft head,
カッコの付け方調子のこき方
how to wear a cap, how things are going,
腹の据え方良い年のこき方
how to hold one's ground, how to have a good year,
脂乗りに乗った濁った目した
riding the gravy train, having a cloudy look,
だらしない身体
sloppy body.
嫌われ方や慕われ方や
How to be disliked, how to be adored,
殴られ方とか綺麗なぶつかり方
how to get hit, or a nice collision,
もっと覚いたい事が山のようにある
there are still mountains of things I want to remember,
のびしろしかないわ
I only have room to grow.
俺らまだのびしろしかないわ
We still only have room to grow.
悪者扱いして来た街で
In the town where I was treated like a villain,
悪者扱いして来たオトナへ
to the adult who was treated like a villain,
変わりゆく俺、鏡の中へ
I change, into the mirror,
尋ねても答えなら yeah yeah yeah
even if I ask, there's no answer, yeah yeah yeah.
去る者追わない引くところ引いて
Don't chase those who leave, pull where you pull,
丸く納めたり軽くいなして
round it up and lightly vanish,
鏡の中で嗤ってるお前
you who are laughing in the mirror,
括れやしなかったわ。たったの三文字で
weren't you bracing yourself? Just three words.
日日重くなる足取りで
With heavy footsteps day by day,
自分の歩幅で闊歩してる
I'm walking at my own pace.
勘ぐるとこ勘ぐり
Guess where, leave where,
割と適当な段取りで
with a fairly casual pacing,
やっと思い付いて来たかも
maybe I've finally started to understand
このポンコツの操縦の仕方を
how to handle this ponkotsu.
19の時の「ついに来たか...」よりももっと清々しい気持ち
With a much fresher feeling than "Finally came..." at 19,
隅田川にかかる勝鬨橋を渡る
Crossing Kachidoki Bridge over the Sumida River,
左手にスカイツリー 右手に東京タワー
Skytree on the left, Tokyo Tower on the right,
俺はその真ん中
I am right in the middle.
サボり方とか甘え方とか
Laziness or spoiling,
逃げ方とか言い訳の仕方とか
running away or making excuses,
やっと覚えてきた身につけてきた
I've finally learned and picked them up.
柔らかい頭
Soft head,
カッコの付け方調子のこき方
how to wear a cap, how things are going,
腹の据え方良い年のこき方
how to hold one's ground, how to have a good year,
脂乗りに乗った濁った目した
riding the gravy train, having a cloudy look,
だらしない身体
sloppy body.
幸せの体感速度は早くなるばかり
The speed of feeling happy only gets faster,
傷が癒えていく速度は遅くなるばかり
the speed at which wounds heal only gets slower,
他人には期待をしないのが今の俺の強み
not expecting anything from others is my strength now,
手荷物でも進める距離なら行くぜ欺き欺き
even with a heavy load, if the distance is manageable, I'll go, deceiving myself.
身の程を知る程に胸を張りいつもの通り
Knowing my own limits, I always puff out my chest,
でも時にしたって良い背伸び
but sometimes a good stretch of the back is in order,
やっと「大人げない」が出来る年
a year where I can finally act "un-adult-like."
小さな枠組みただの数字
Small framework, just a number,
縛られずにでも腹くくり
unbound, yet with a firm belly,
あの日の俺が立ち止まる程にデカくそびえ立つ
so big and towering that the me of that day stops in its tracks.
隅田川にかかる勝鬨橋を渡る
Crossing Kachidoki Bridge over the Sumida River,
重なるスカイツリー 東京タワーと真ん中の頼りない背中
heavy Skytree, right in the middle of Tokyo Tower, with an unreliable back.
サボり方とか甘え方とか
Laziness or spoiling,
逃げ方とか言い訳の仕方とか
running away or making excuses,
やっと覚えてきた身につけてきた
I've finally learned and picked them up.
柔らかい頭
Soft head,
春の風に吹かれて 綿毛 ふわり 横切っていく
Blowin' in the spring breeze, fluffy dandelion fluff drifts across.
どこまで行くのかな 僕もたどり着けるかな
I wonder how far it goes, and if I'll reach there too.
ふっと歩みを止めて 振り返って見る自分は
When I suddenly stop and look back at myself,
どんな風に映ってる? 純白のハナミズキ揺れる
how do I look? The pure white dogwood sways.
ちょっと、君に会いたい 1分1秒、分かち合いたい
I just want to see you, share every minute and second together.
優しいあの声今なんか聞きたくなったよ
I suddenly wanted to hear that gentle voice of yours right now.
のびしろしかないわ
There's nowhere to go but up!
俺らまだのびしろしかないわ
We've still got so much room to grow!
悪くないよ、ねえ！
Not bad at all!
悪いね
My bad.
はっけよい 残った人生を 探し続けてた
Wrestling on, I kept searching for my remaining life.
ゲットー 素っ気もクソもない いつももっと
In the ghetto, nothing cares, always wanting more.
夢中になって もういいかい 何回も聞いたって
Getting absorbed, "Are you ready yet?" hearing it over and over.
待ってよ ぜーんぜんかんたんじちゃって
Wait up, it feels way too simple.
もういいよって バイバイすたってなんだってんだ
Saying "Enough is enough" and bye-bye, what's that all about?
だまっておれは なぜだか 知ってんだ
Silently, for some reason, I know why.
着飾った愛を語って だって行き詰まってジャンキー
Talking about dressed-up love, hitting a dead end like a junkie.
くすぶってやっきになって 後ろに余白は アキアキです
Smoldering, getting desperate, I'm sick of having empty space behind me.
本当 アキアキです
Really, I'm so sick of it.
着飾った愛を語って だって行き詰まってジャンキー
Talking about dressed-up love, hitting a dead end like a junkie.
くすぶってやっきになって 後ろに余白は アキアキです
Smoldering, getting desperate, I'm sick of having empty space behind me.
本当 アキアキです
Really, I'm so sick of it.
アキアキです
So sick of it!
着飾った愛を語って だって行き詰まってジャンキー
Talking about dressed-up love, hitting a dead end like a junkie.
疑ってはいずっくばって そんな劣等感に アキアキです
Doubling down and groveling, I'm sick of such inferiority complexes.
本当 アキアキです
Really, I'm so sick of it.
もうためんで単調なジャンキーは 結構です
I've had enough of half-baked, monotonous junkies.
変わり映えのしない毎日を 燃やし続けてた
Burning through a dull, unchanging everyday life.
ゲットー 素っ気もクソもない いつもずっと
In the ghetto, nothing cares, always and forever.
立ち止まって 興味ないととか 関係といっそ
Stopping in my tracks, saying "not interested" and cutting ties.
しょうもないヒント 散々荒らしちゃって
Messing up trivial hints completely.
信用ないもう 感嘆見栄張っちゃって
Losing trust, showing off with fake awe.
だまっておれは なぜだか 知ってんだ
Silently, for some reason, I know why.
着飾った愛を語って だって行き詰まってジャンキー
Talking about dressed-up love, hitting a dead end like a junkie.
くすぶってやっきになって 後ろに余白は アキアキです
Smoldering, getting desperate, I'm sick of having empty space behind me.
本当 アキアキです
Really, I'm so sick of it.
着飾った愛を語って だって行き詰まってジャンキー
Talking about dressed-up love, hitting a dead end like a junkie.
偏った愛に染まって 窮屈こうそめも アキアキです
Dyed in biased love, I'm sick of the suffocating confinement too.
本当 アキアキです
Really, I'm so sick of it.
着飾った愛を語って だって行き詰まってジャンキー
Talking about dressed-up love, hitting a dead end like a junkie.
疑ってはいずっくばって そんな劣等感に アキアキです
Doubling down and groveling, I'm sick of such inferiority complexes.
本当 アキアキです
Really, I'm so sick of it.
もうためんで単調なジャンキーは 結構です
I've had enough of half-baked, monotonous junkies.
長い長い長い 未来の想像を描いてく
Painting long, long, long imaginations of the future.
時代じゃない 時代じゃない 自分を信じたってさ
Even if I believe in myself, unsuited for the times, unsuited for the times...
夢中でいたいし 夢中でいたいし 思っていたいし 歌っていたいよ 感情を
I want to be absorbed, I want to be absorbed, I want to keep thinking, I want to sing my emotions.
着飾った愛を語って だって行き詰まってジャンキー
Talking about dressed-up love, hitting a dead end like a junkie.
偏った愛に染まって 窮屈こうそめも アキアキです
Dyed in biased love, I'm sick of the suffocating confinement too.
本当 アキアキです
Really, I'm so sick of it.
着飾った愛を語って だって行き詰まってジャンキー
Talking about dressed-up love, hitting a dead end like a junkie.
疑ってはいずっくばって そんな劣等感に アキアキです
Doubling down and groveling, I'm sick of such inferiority complexes.
本当 アキアキです
Really, I'm so sick of it.
着飾った愛を語って だって行き詰まってジャンキー
Talking about dressed-up love, hitting a dead end like a junkie.
偏った愛に染まって 窮屈こうそめも アキアキです
Dyed in biased love, I'm sick of the suffocating confinement too.
もうためんで単調なジャンキーは 結構です
I've had enough of half-baked, monotonous junkies.
いやー！楽しいね！
Yay! That was so fun!
ここまで出演してくれたゲストのみんなも、ありがとー！
Thank you so much to all the guests who performed with us up to this point!
いやー、ライブもね、終盤に差し掛かってきたけど
Man, the live concert is reaching its climax too, but...
今年1年、どんな年だったかなあ？
What kind of year was this past year, I wonder?
わためはね、
As for Watame...
とにかくあっという間だったなあ。
it just went by in a flash.
いろんな人の歌のライブゲストにも出させてもらったり、
I got to appear as a guest on various people's live concerts,
今年のわための記念配信にも、いろんなたくさんのホロメンを呼べてね、とっても嬉しかったし、楽しかった。
and for this year's anniversary stream, I invited so many Holomem friends—I was so happy and had so much fun.
そんな1年だったような気がします。
It feels like that kind of year.
あとはね、いろんな企画？ギリギリ悪くないわためとか、
And also, various projects? Like "Barely Not Bad Watame,"
あと、角巻わためのハバナイスデイとか、まあ企画とかに挑戦したり、
and Tsunomaki Watame's Have a Nice Day, taking on challenges with various projects,
あとは今年もね、たくさん配信したし、もう何より駆け抜けた1年だったなと思います。
and I streamed a lot this year too, and more than anything, I feel like it was a year of running full speed ahead.
ずっとね、わためいとのみんなと一緒だったから、本当に楽しかったよ、泣いちゃうよ。
I've always been together with all the Watamates, so it was truly fun... I'm gonna cry.
わためいともそう思ってくれてると、嬉しいです。
I'd be happy if the Watamates feel the same way.
いや、コメントでもね、「あっという間だった」とか、
Well, in the comments too, like "it went by in a flash,"
ハートとかもね、いっぱい送ってくれてるけど、やっぱそうだよね、今年あっという間だったよね。
and sending lots of hearts, but yeah, it's true, this year went by in a flash, didn't it?
今年は折り曲も、去年ほどじゃなかったけど、
This year, original songs, though not as many as last year,
あ、な、な、なんだったっけ？なんだっけ？もう涙をこらえるのでいっぱいで、
ah, wh-wh-what was it again? What was it? I'm already holding back tears so much that
曲名が出てこないよ！
the song title isn't coming out!
「夢見る羊」とか「君色ハナビュティ」とか、
"Yumemiru Hitsuji," "Kimiiro Hanabizuki,"
あとは、かりちゃんとのね、ラップ2バージョンとか、もう4曲ほど、5曲ほどかな？作れて、
and also, the rap two-version with Calli, made about four or five songs,
本当みんなのおかげです。ありがとうございます。
and it's truly thanks to everyone. Thank you so much.
英語のラップにもね、頑張って、もう、「やだ！無理！」って言いながら挑戦したり、作詞も何曲か書かせていただいたり、挑戦の年だったなと思います。
I worked hard on the English rap too, saying "No! No way!" while taking on challenges, and wrote lyrics for a few songs—I feel like it was a year of challenges.
この3年間駆け抜けてきたけど、
I've run through these past three years, but
まだまだ叶えたい夢やみんなと一緒にやりたいこととかもたくさんあるから、これからも挑戦を続けていくという気持ちを込めて歌いたいと思います。聞いてください、「My song」。
there are still so many dreams I want to fulfill and things I want to do together with everyone, so with the feeling of continuing to take on challenges, I want to sing this. Please listen to "My song."
手にしたもの以外が綺麗に見えた
Everything outside of what I held in my hands looked so bright
どうせこんなもんかとが口癖だった
"That's just how it is" was always on my lips
うすら笑いばっかが得意になった
I became a pro at offering hollow, bitter smiles
けど一番笑えんのはこのプライドだ
But the one thing I couldn't laugh at was this pride of mine
一生懸命なんか全部無駄だったんだって
Thinking that all my earnest efforts were totally in vain,
もう嫌になった
I grew so sick of it all
逃げたくないって聞こえたこれは僕の声
"I don't want to run away," I heard—this is my voice
1回 10回 100回 挫折したって挑戦は続けるよ
Once, ten times, a hundred times—even if I stumble, I'll keep on challenging
まだ足りない全部持ってる山ない雨の中
Still not enough, within the endless, ceaseless rain
ずっと考えて考えて考えて見つけ出した僕だけのコンパスを証明したいんだよな そうだろ
Thinking and thinking until I found my own compass—I want to prove it, right?
そうだろ
Right?
焦り上がる心拍数に嘘をつくより
Rather than lying to my racing heartbeat,
自分を落ち着ける日には食わいらない
I don't need a shield on days I need to calm myself
それも今日を境に置き換えたならさ
If I replace that starting from today,
今日もまた挑むべきハードルがほら見えただろう
Look, another hurdle I must face is already in sight, isn't it?
葛藤の隙間で錆びない生命をひねり出せるか
Can I squeeze out an un-rusting life from the cracks of inner conflict?
出ないのならとっくに諦めてるよ
If I couldn't, I would have given up long ago
更新のしねんで歌ったって届くわけじゃない
Even if I sing with all my heart, it won't necessarily reach you
素晴らしい
How wonderful
僕らの現実は残酷だ 曖昧を削り取って尖らせまた歌って諦める
Our reality is cruel—shaving away ambiguity, sharpening it, singing again, and giving up
例えなら過去に捨ててきた 愛してたんだよ
If it's an example, I left it in the past—I loved it so much
愛してたんだよ
I loved it so much
立ち止まる度に進みたくなる星を まだ行こう
Every time I stop, I want to move toward the stars—let's keep going
小さくて頼りなくて 不安そうな歩幅が 繋がって
Small, hesitant, and uncertain steps connect together
歌い出す 僕を聴いてくれ
Please listen to me as I start to sing.
みんな、ありがとう！
Thank you, everyone!
一回じゃ足りない 世界征服 挑戦は続けるよ
One time isn't enough, world domination, I'll keep on challenging.
まだ足りない 手を握ってる
Still not enough, holding your hand.
やまない雨の中 ずっと考えて
Inside the unending rain, I kept thinking and thinking.
食べて考えて 見つけてみせるぜ
Thinking and searching, I'll find it.
僕だけの 笑顔から はじめたいんだよな
I want to start with my very own smile.
もし明日なら 誇っていこうな
If tomorrow comes, let's walk with pride.
4年目も 一緒に歩いてこうね
Let's walk together into our fourth year too.
最後の曲です。聴いてください。
This is the final song. Please listen.
新曲「Happy day to you」！
My new song, 'Happy day to you'!
今日は年に一度、特別な日
Today is a special day, once a year.
君と一緒に今お祝いをしよう
Let's celebrate right now together with you.
ケーキの上 ローソク 火をつけて
Lighting the candles on top of the cake,
「おめでとう」笑顔が溢れるよ
With 'Congratulations,' smiles overflow.
生まれてきたこと それは 偶然？奇跡？かもしれない
Being born into this world... is it coincidence? Or maybe a miracle?
でもせっかくなら 日々をもっと
But since we're here, let's make our days even more...
happy! enjoy! さあ行こう！
happy! enjoy! Now let's go!
雲の絨毯 探し食べてみたり
Searching for and tasting a carpet of clouds,
魔法を使って 空を飛んだり
Using magic to fly through the sky,
誰かを救う ヒーローになったり
Becoming a hero who saves someone,
なんでもできそうな気がするね
It feels like we can do anything.
そんな奇跡みたいな日々を ずっと もっと
Those miraculous days, forever and ever more...
なんでもない 日々は意地悪で
Ordinary days can be mean sometimes,
くちびる噛みしめる 時もあるよね
Times when we bite our lips in frustration happen too.
落ち込んで凹んで 浮かない顔
Feeling down and depressed with a gloomy face,
大丈夫、笑顔がこぼれるよ
It's alright, a smile will spill over.
生まれてきたこと それを 後悔しちゃう？かもしれない
Being born into this world... might you regret it?
でもせっかくなら 日々をもっと
But since we're here, let's make our days even more...
happiness! joyful! ほら行こう！
happiness! joyful! Come on, let's go!
小さな幸せ 積み上げて
Piling up small happinesses,
世界で一つだけの宝物
The one and only treasure in the world.
君が生きた証 抱きしめて
Embrace the proof that you lived.
生まれてきてくれてありがとう
Thank you for being born into this world.
君も、そこの君も一緒に 同じ時代に生まれた奇跡たち
You too, and you over there as well—miracles born in the same era.
来年も再来年も一緒に ここで笑ってお祝いしよう
Next year and the year after that too, let's celebrate and smile together here.
そんな奇跡みたいな日々を ずっと もっと
Those miraculous days, forever and ever more...
happy happy day to you!
皆さんこんばんは！ここで角巻にゅーすのお時間です。
Good evening, everyone! It's time for Tsunomaki News.
なんと、この後10時、角巻わためさん活動3周年グッズが販売となります！イェーヘイ！
And guess what? At 10 PM today, Tsunomaki Watame's 3rd Anniversary goods go on sale! Yeah-hey!
内容は、アクリルスタンド、グラス、わためいとぬいぐるみ、そしてわためのおうたボリューム2.5の4点セットです。
The set includes 4 items: an acrylic stand, a glass, a Watamate plushie, and Watame no Uta Vol. 2.5.
まずは、こちらの商品の、アクリルスタンドです。
First up is this item: the acrylic stand.
実は幅野みたいに、わためと一緒におでかけするように作ってあります。イラストは佐倉おりこ先生に書いていただきました！みんなで旅行に行こー！
Actually, it's designed so you can go out together with Watame, like on a trip. The illustration was drawn by Orico Sakura-sensei! Let's all go on a trip!
続いての商品は、グラスです。たぶん届くのが春以降になると思うんですが、その時にみんながごくごく飲めるように、素敵なちょっと大きめのグラスにしました。
The next item is the glass. It will probably arrive around spring, so I made it a nice, slightly larger glass so everyone can drink heartily then.
そして3点目！わためいとぬいぐるみ！これ実はわためが欲しかったんだよね（笑）。あれ、画像まだかな？
And the 3rd item! The Watamate plushie! Actually, Watame wanted this one. Wait, is the image not up yet?
画像、あ、きたー！めっちゃ可愛い！今日のステージにもいたわためいとそっくりです。めちゃくちゃいーい！
The image, ah, it's here! So cute! It looks just like the Watamates on stage today. It's super good!
そしてそして、最後にわためのおうたボリューム2.5です。今回はシングルくらいの曲数なので、2.5とさせていただきました！ママいつも本当にありがとー！
And finally, Watame no Uta Vol. 2.5. Since it's about the number of songs on a single, we called it 2.5! Mama, thank you so much always!
本日24時から各種音楽サイトでも公開されますので、こちらもチェックをよろしくお願いします！
It will also be released on various music sites starting at midnight today, so please check that out too!
そして、フルセットをご購入いただいたお客さまにはなんと！角巻わため箔押し複製サイン入りチェキ風ブロマイドカード＋特典ボイスがついてきます！これは買うしかありません！
And for customers who purchase the full set, you get a cheki-style bromide card with Tsunomaki Watame's signature + bonus voice! You simply have to buy this!
ということで、以上が3周年グッズになります。わためいとのことを考えて、少しでも喜んでもらえるように、スタッフさんとかと念入りに打ち合わせをしていいものにしました。ぜひチェックしてください！
So, those are the 3rd anniversary goods. We had thorough meetings with the staff to make it into something good so it would make you happy. Please check it out!
まだ本篇は続きます！そのあとアフターライブもあるから遊びに来てね！
The main show continues! There's also an after-live afterwards, so come play!
以上、角巻にゅーすでした！
That's all for Tsunomaki News!
チャン×チャン 逢！！チキチキバンバン
Chance x Chance! Meeting!! Chiki Chiki Ban Ban
哀！？チキチキチチャンチャン
Sorrow!? Chiki Chiki Chan Chan
呼呼！チキチキバンバン
Ah! Chiki Chiki Ban Ban
愛！！チュキチュキチュキバンバン
Love!! Chuki Chuki Chuki Ban Ban
HIGH チキチキバンバン
HIGH Chiki Chiki Ban Ban
哀！？チキチキチチャンチャン
Sorrow!? Chiki Chiki Chan Chan
呼呼！チキチキバンバン
Ah! Chiki Chiki Ban Ban
愛！！チュキチュキ
Love!! Chuki Chuki
猫も杓子も みんな気まぐれで辛い
Everyone is moody and it's tough
酔えばテキーラ
If you get drunk, tequila
有る無き妄想連続でピーカン
Continuous wild delusions are clear blue skies
夢はパンドラ ほら 開けたたくなる
Dreams are Pandora, come on, you want to open them
みんな期待して パリピょん
Everyone expect it, you party people
今夜 富士山 昇らん 者分からない
Tonight, you won't know unless you climb Mount Fuji
決戦も週末の宿命
The decisive battle is the fate of the weekend
チャン×チャン 逢！！チキチキバンバン
Chance x Chance! Meeting!! Chiki Chiki Ban Ban
何も勿体ぶらず楽しめ fever tonight
Don't hold back, enjoy the fever tonight
チャン×チャン 哀！？チキチキバンバン！
Chance x Chance! Sorrow!? Chiki Chiki Ban Ban!
何度むしゃくしゃしたって party tonight
No matter how frustrated you get, party tonight
チャン×チャン 呼呼！！チキチキバンバン
Chance x Chance! Ah! Chiki Chiki Ban Ban
愚か者ほど high とかす 完全 社会
The more foolish you are, the higher you get in this perfect society
チャン×チャン 愛！！チキチキバンバン
Chance x Chance! Love!! Chiki Chiki Ban Ban
みんなスーパースターの卵さ diva tonight
Everyone is a budding superstar, diva tonight
チャン×チャン 呼呼！！チキチキバンバン
Chance x Chance! Ah! Chiki Chiki Ban Ban
愚か者ほど high とかす 完全 社会
The more foolish you are, the higher you get in this perfect society
チャン×チャン 愛！！チキチキバンバン
Chance x Chance! Love!! Chiki Chiki Ban Ban
みんなスーパースターの卵さ diva tonight
Everyone is a budding superstar, diva tonight
チャン×チャン 逢！！チキチキバンバン
Chance x Chance! Meeting!! Chiki Chiki Ban Ban
哀！？チキチキチチャンチャン
Sorrow!? Chiki Chiki Chan Chan
呼呼！チキチキバンバン
Ah! Chiki Chiki Ban Ban
愛！！チュキチュキチュキバンバン
Love!! Chuki Chuki Chuki Ban Ban
HIGH チキチキバンバン
HIGH Chiki Chiki Ban Ban
哀！？チキチキチチャンチャン
Sorrow!? Chiki Chiki Chan Chan
呼呼！チキチキバンバン
Ah! Chiki Chiki Ban Ban
愛！！チュキチュキ
Love!! Chuki Chuki
チャンス×チャンス
Chance x chance
逢！！ チキチキ バンバン
Meet! Chiki Chiki Bam Bam
哀！？ チキチキ チャン チャン
Sorrow!? Chiki Chiki Chan Chan
唞呼！！ チキチキ バンバン
Ah!! Chiki Chiki Bam Bam
愛！！ チュキチュキチュキ バンバン
Love!! Chuki Chuki Chuki Bam Bam
high チキチキ バンバン
High Chiki Chiki Bam Bam
哀！？ チキチキ チャン チャン
Sorrow!? Chiki Chiki Chan Chan
唞呼！！ チキチキ バンバン
Ah!! Chiki Chiki Bam Bam
愛！！ チュキチュキ
Love!! Chuki Chuki
猫も杓子も みんな 気狂いでツラァァイ
Everyone, even your cats, are crazy, it's frustrating!
酔えばテーラあらぬ妄想 連続で閃き
Drunk on tequila, your head is full of delusions
夢はパンドラ ほら 開けたくな る～
The dream is Pandora's box, makes you want to open it~
みんな期待して パリ ピィ ヤァ
Everyone waiting, party people yeah!
今夜フジヤマ 登らにゃわからな～い
It'll hit the peak like Mt. Fuji, you won't know until you climb
決戦は週末の宿命
The final battle is the fate of the weekend
チャンス×チャンス
Chance x chance
逢！！ チキチキ バンバン
Meet! Chiki Chiki Bam Bam
何も勿体ぶらず 謳え フィーバー トゥナイト
Enjoy the fever tonight without holding back
チャンス×チャンス
Chance x chance
逢！！ チキチキ バンバン
Meet! Chiki Chiki Bam Bam
哀！？ チキチキ チャン チャン
Sorrow!? Chiki Chiki Chan Chan
唞呼！！ チキチキ バンバン
Ah!! Chiki Chiki Bam Bam
愛！！ チュキチュキチュキ バンバン
Love!! Chuki Chuki Chuki Bam Bam
high チキチキ バンバン
High Chiki Chiki Bam Bam
哀！？ チキチキ チャン チャン
Sorrow!? Chiki Chiki Chan Chan
唞呼！！ チキチキ バンバン
Ah!! Chiki Chiki Bam Bam
愛！！ チュキチュキ
Love!! Chuki Chuki
何度ムシャクシャしたって パーリー トゥナイト
No matter how many times you're frustrated, party tonight
チャンス×チャンス
Chance x chance
逢！！ チキチキ バンバン
Meet! Chiki Chiki Bam Bam
愚か者ほど high と化す 完全社会
A perfect society where fools become high
チャンス×チャンス
Chance x chance
愛！！ チキチキ バンバン
Love!! Chiki Chiki Bam Bam
みんなスーパースターの卵さ ディーヴァ トゥナイト
Everyone is a superstar in training, diva tonight
グラス上げ グラマラスしない？
Will you raise your glass and be glamorous?
デモもダコも皆要らない hands up
We don't need 'buts' or 'noes', hands up
倫理で警告しない！
Don't warn with ethics!
ジャパニーズ プリティ 密かに今 沸騰
Japanese beauty, secretly boiling now
グラス上げ グラシアスしたい
I want to raise a glass and say 'gracious'
飲めばノリ良くあっけらかんとせよ yeah
The more you drink, the higher you'll start to fly, yes!
ブランク捨て バウンスして ジャンプ
Discard blanks, bounce and jump
夢マキシマム 熱く dancing, oh yeah
Dreams at maximum, hot dancing, oh yeah
いつも理性はどうして 萎縮がちで
Why is reason always so timid?
エネルギーを満たし 1000本テエーラ
Fill your energy, 1,000 bottles of tequila!
song! love! ソーラーで空飛ぶ ジュータン
Song! Love! Flying in the sky with solar energy
真っ逆さま 下向かないで
Upside down, don't look down
陰気じゃダメ インフレして給え
Don't be gloomy, inflate it
ダラダラする間に ending 人生
While you're lazing around, life is ending
未練は no shining 軌道
Regret is not a shining path
歯に衣着せず 総力戦
Speak frankly, all-out war
oh, baby 小賢しいね
Oh honey, you're smartass
ha-ha-ha-high 一斉 テエーラ
Ha-ha-ha-high all together tequila
「前だけ向いてりゃ良いでしょう？」
"You can just look forward, right?"
「燃え盛っちゃうけど良いでしょう？」
"It's burning up, but that's fine, right?"
もう少し play god
Play god a little more
もう少し bang out
Bang out a little more
明日が来るけど 機嫌はどうだい？
Tomorrow is coming, how are you feeling?
ほらほら 次回に スポット当てんな
Hey hey, don't spotlight the next time
「いつまで歌う気だっけ？」
"How much longer are you going to sing?"
8時間！？
8 hours!?